Central Texas glass plate negative collection 100.2002
University Archives, Texas State University
Central Texas glass plate negative collection
circa 1882-1911
University Archives, Texas State University https://www.univarchives.txstate.edu/
University Archives, Texas State University
100.2002
2.17 Linear Feet 4 boxes
46 items
This collection consists of 46 glass plate negatives showing images of San Antonio and San Marcos, Texas, and the surrounding area, as well as portraits dating from around 1892-1911. Notable images include Battle of Flowers parade, Fort Sam Houston, the Hays County Courthouse, the First United Methodist Church, and the Belgar-Cahill Lime Kiln.
Conditions Governing Access
Images are completely digitized. Access to original glass plate negatives is restricted due to their fragile nature. Researchers are encouraged to use the digital images available at the online exhibit. Please contact the University Archives for more information at univarchives@txstate.edu.
Historical note
The glass plate negatives in this collection are of the "dry" type, which was a significant innovation. Before their invention in 1871, photographers had to prepare the glass plates and apply emulsions, expose, and develop them while still "wet." To process, or develop, the images, photographers needed a place that was free from light, a "darkroom." Thus, wet plate photographers needed either to remain close to their darkrooms or recreate them in the field.
Dry plate emulsions did not have the same time limitations as wet plate. Their stability allowed for greater mobility and convenience. Photographers could wait to expose their plates and then store them back in the box until they could be developed. Nevertheless, glass plates remained fragile and surprisingly heavy.
While dry glass plates allowed the practice of photography to spread to a larger number of people, it was the invention of roll film (1887) and Kodak's Brownie box camera (1900) which made photography widely accessible to the general public. Roll film was stable, lightweight, and a roll could be mailed to Kodak for developing and printing.
The photographer for this collection was using dry plates, we know they carried these heavy and fragile plates to locations to expose them, then carried them back to the darkroom to process them. The photographer likely needed considerable chemical and technical knowlege, specialized darkroom materials and equipment, and a dedicated work space to develop their plates and print photographs.
The glass plates arrived in Cramer's Lightning Dry Plate negative boxes. Mr. Cramer was a national supplier of dry plates beginning 1883.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 46 glass plate negatives, measuring 4x5 inches, found in G. Cramer Dry Plate Company boxes. The photographer is unknown. Identified images within the collection were taken in San Antonio, Texas and San Marcos, Texas. These include views of the Hays County Courthouse, the First United Methodist Church, and the Belgar-Cahill Lime Kiln in San Marcos, Texas. A street view of San Marcos, Texas is also present. Others depict scenes from the Battle of Flowers parade in San Antonio, Texas. A few images show soldiers in formation engaged in military drills at Fort Sam Houston with Lambermot home and St. Paul's Episcopal Church in the background. Others show armed men on outdoor excursions or posed beside horse drawn carriages. Unidentified images depict men, women, and children in various forms of outdoor recreation, viewing machinery, or intentionally posed for portraiture. There are also images of various types of machinery. Dates for some negatives have been estimated upon their subjects. All others probably date between 1892-1911.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were found at Goodwill in San Marcos, Texas and then donated by Mike Hughes and Helen Van Wieren in August 22, 2016.
Related Materials
See also: Battle of Flowers Parade photos, University of Texas at San Antonio. As well as the San Marcos Daily Record photographic negative collection (100.SMDR).
Index Terms
Subjects
Photography -- Texas; Frontier and pioneer life -- Texas
Document Types
Glass plate negatives; negatives (photographs)
Places
Texas -- Description and travel; Hays County (Tex.) -- History
- Six men with campfire and cookery tools in foreground, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_001; Six men all wearing hats with campfire and cooking tools in foreground. Five men appear to be white, and one appears to be black. Two of the men are standing. Three men have pistols in holsters at waist. One is smoking and crouched to the ground, another is holding a metal cup and kneeling, and anther is using a piece of cloth to hold a pan which is resting on a wooden branch. Trees in background. (Box 1)
- Three white men standing on rocks in unknown river with truss bridge in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_002; One man standing with hands at waist on large rock in an unknown river. Two other men on another rock behind him. Bridge in the far background. (Box 1)
- White woman reading at Jacob's Well, Wimberley, Texas., circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_003 (Box 1)
- Man standing on tall smoke stack, unknown industrial building, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_004 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Probably San Marcos Electric, Light, & Power Company, San Marcos, Texas.
- Man standing on tall smoke stack, unknown industrial building, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_005 (Box 1)
- Hays County Courthouse in San Marcos, Texas, circa 1882-1908; Goodwill-glass-plates_006; The Hays County Courthouse (1882-1908)in San Marcos, Texas. Designed by F.E. Ruffini. (Box 1)
- San Antonio Street, south side of the Square, San Marcos, Texas, circa 1900; Goodwill-glass-plates_007; San Antonio Street between Austin (now LBJ) and Guadalupe Streets, San Marcos, Texas. From left to right: T.A. Porter, Fish & Oysters, Lone Star Bakery, and H.A. Nitzsche. (Box 1)
- Soldiers marching on the field, Fort Sam Houston, San Antonio, Texas. Second building from the left is Lambermont House, also known as Terrell Castle, circa 1984-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_008 (Box 1)
- Battle of Flowers Parade, Commerce Street, San Antonio, Texas., circa 1907-1911; Goodwill-glass-plates_009; Battle of Flowers Parade on Commerce Street between Navarro and Saint Mary's streets in San Antonio Texas. Can see part of the D&A Oppenheimer Bank awning and Alamo Music Store. (Box 1)
- Battle of Flowers Parade, Commerce Street, San Antonio, Texas., circa 1907-1911; Goodwill-glass-plates_010; Battle of Flowers Parade on Commerce Street between Navarro and Saint Mary's streets in San Antonio Texas. Can see Alamo Music Store storefront. (Box 1)
- Battle of Flowers Parade, Commerce Street, San Antonio, Texas., circa 1907-1911; Goodwill-glass-plates_011; Mounted units in the Battle of Flowers Parade on Commerce Street between Navarro and Saint Mary's streets in San Antonio Texas. Floral decorations covering the carriage, the large boutonnières worn by the mounted soldiers, and the lavishly decorated hats and umbrellas of the women on-board. Can see part of the D&A Oppenheimer Bank awning and Alamo Music Store. (Box 1)
- Commerce Street, San Antonio, Texas., circa 1907-1911; Goodwill-glass-plates_012; Commerce Street between Navarro and Saint Mary's streets in San Antonio Texas. Can see Alamo Music Store storefront. (Box 1)
- Soldiers marching in formation on the field, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_013 (Box 1)
- Mounted units on field. Fort Sam Houston, San Antonio, Texas, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_014; Clock tower that overlooks Fort Sam Houston's Quadrangle seen along right edge of image. (Box 1)
- Three people on top of Belgar-Cahill Lime Kiln in San Marcos, Texas, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_015; Two women and one man on top of Lime Kiln. (Box 1)
- Ten people sitting on ground around a picnic, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_016 (Box 2)
- View of double bend in unknown waterway, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_017 (Box 2)
- Seven people including children by a tree, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_018; Group portrait of seven people including children. Rocking chair and hedge in background. (Box 2)
- View of unknown machine room containing belt driven electric generators, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_019 (Box 2)
- Three people sitting on ground having a picnic, river in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_020 (Box 2)
- View of downtown San Marcos, Texas, taken from Chautauqua Hill, circa 1893 and 1908; Goodwill-glass-plates_021; View of downtown San Marcos, Texas, taken from Chautauqua Hill where Old Main on Texas State University stands today. Includes Hays County Courthouse and the First United Methodist Church. (Box 2)
- Damaged negative, circa 1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_022 (Box 2)
- "Homestead Queen" poster compliments of Goodfellow-Brooks Shoe Co, circa 1903; Goodwill-glass-plates_023 (Box 2)
  Advertisement for the lithograph dated 1903
- Three white people fishing while on tree trunk along river, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_024 (Box 2)
- White woman and infant sitting on rocking chair outside along house, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_025 (Box 2)
- Toddler with brimmed hat with bushes and picket fence in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_026 (Box 2)
- Damaged double exposed image with two couples and a child, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_027 (Box 2)
- Four black women in front of wooden house, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_028 (Box 2)
- Parke County Courthouse in Rockville, Indiana, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_029 (Box 2)
- White woman posing on porch of house with another house in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_030 (Box 3)
- Rocky slope with four figures on horses at top, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_031 (Box 3)
- View of unknown waterway with tree in foreground, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_032 (Box 3)
- San Marcos River, San Marcos, Texas. View from the powerhouse looking east towards what is now the Sewell Park Bridge, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_033; View from the powerhouse looking east towards what is now the Sewell Park Bridge, San Marcos River, San Marcos, Texas. Carriages on bridge and also traversing the river along with people on horseback. (Box 3)
- Four people at base of a tree, one man and three women with river in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_034 (Box 3)
- Two figures in canopied carriage with barn in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_035 (Box 3)
- Group of four white individuals and one black youngster along stream bank near part of a portable steam engine, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_036 (Box 3)
- People carrying band instruments and wearing uniform, one individual carrying banner, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_037 (Box 3)
- White man holding bucket next to portable steam engine with belt system. Group four white individuals and one black youngster in background across stream, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_038 (Box 3)
- Three white children and donkey, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_039 (Box 3)
- Six people, three white men, one white women standing in buggy, one black youngster kneeling, and one black man holding pick axe, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_040 (Box 3)
- Toddler and infant on porch. Infant in rocking chair, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_041 (Box 3)
- Three people, two white women, one sitting on tree branch, and a white man. River in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_042 (Box 3)
- Three men, one holding rifle, with horses and carriage. Wooden building in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_043 (Box 3)
- Three people in horse drawn buggy going through stream. Four individuals sitting along bank in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_044 (Box 3)
- Six white men with hats sitting or crouched with horse in saddles in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_045 (Box 3)
- Soldiers with horses and cannon in field. Buildings in background, circa 1880s-1900s; Goodwill-glass-plates_046 (Box 4)
- G. Cramer Dry Plate boxes, circa 1880s-1900s
  Original housing of negatives.